<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter unto a person of honour &amp; quality containing some animadversions upon the Bishop of VVorcester's letter.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B417A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895414</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2323:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter unto a person of honour &amp; quality containing some animadversions upon the Bishop of VVorcester's letter.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 16[62]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: D.E., i.e. Edward Bagshaw.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Morley, George.  The Bishop of Worcester's letter to a friend for vindication of himself from Mr. Baxter's calumny.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morley, George, 1597-1684. --  Bishop of Worcester's letter to a friend for vindication of himself from Mr. Baxter's calumny --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152814:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152814:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER unto a PERSON of Honour &amp; Quality, Containing ſome ANIMADVERSIONS upon the Biſhop of Worceſter's LETTER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152814:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152814:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable and Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to thank You for the laſt piece of Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement you gave me, in ſending the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Letter, and I wiſh you would have let me enjoyed the ſatisfaction I took in reading it, without obliging me to give You my ſenſe upon it: For beſides my unwillingneſs to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in a Perſonal quarrell, it will not, I think, be very ſafe for any to engage againſt ſo angry an adverſary, which I ſhall be thought to do, though I reſolve to ſpeak nothing but Truth in the Character I intend to give of him; And it is briefly this, That, in fewer leaves I never yet read more Paſſion, which is ſo very predominant, that his diſorderly &amp; abrupt ſtile doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together partake of it; ſo that the Biſhops beſt way will be, to get his Heat miſtaken for Zeal, for elſe it may juſtly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſomething that hath a worſe Name, and which, in the Dog-daies will be very dangerous.</p>
            <p>This being, Sir, my Judgement upon the whole Letter, You may well expect that I ſhould make it good, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from particular inſtances; but before I do this I muſt deal impartially, and aſſure you, that as to the main Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, I think the Biſhop hath much the better of Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> For if the Queſtion between them, was as Dr. <hi>Gunning</hi> and Dr. <hi>Pearſon</hi> do atteſt, ſuch a command is ſo evidently lawfull, that I ſhall much wonder if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> did ever diſpute it; and till he doth clearly diſprove that that was not the thing in Queſtion, I muſt needs think that he hath much forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in making an Imperfect and Partial Relation.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152814:3"/>
            <p>Setting therefore aſide the buſineſs of that particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt (wherein You ſee how much I am inclined to favour the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhop) there are other things in his Letter of general concernment, which I think liable to juſt Exception; As</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he ſuppoſeth there is ſo ſtrict an Union, and ſo inſeparable a Dependance between <hi>Kings and Biſhops, that they must ſtand and fall together; and all who are enemies to the one, muſt needs be enemies to the other.</hi> I know very well this Axiom is much talked of, and ſome advantage may be taken to confirm it, from the event of our late Warres: You know likewiſe, Sir, how much my Judgement is for the Order of Biſhops; and how Paſſionate a Lover I am both of the Kings Perſon and Government, but yet, being thus called by You to declare the truth, though contrary to my own Humour and Intereſt, I muſt needs ſay, 1. It is clear from Story, that <hi>Kings</hi> were in all parts of the world, in their moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Eſtate, before ever <hi>Biſhops</hi> were heard of; and no reaſon can be given, why what hath once been, may not with the ſame terms of convenience be again. 2. <hi>Biſhops</hi> as they are by Law eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> are purely the <hi>Kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Miniſters, in the management of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs;</hi> which his Majeſty may conferre upon what order of men he pleaſes, though they be as much <hi>Lay-perſons</hi> as You and I are. It is therefore very injurious to the <hi>Kings Authority,</hi> to averre that He could not otherwiſe uphold and maintain it, then by preſerving the Undue, and, as ſome think, Antichriſtian Dignity and Prelation of his inferiour Officers. 3. <hi>Biſhops</hi> are ſo little uſefull to ſupport the <hi>Regal Dignity</hi> (which is founded upon a diſtinct Baſis of its own) that upon enquiry it will be found, how none have been greater enemies to the True and Undoubted Soveraignty of Princes, then ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops themſelves: for by their Officious, and ſcarce warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, intermedling in Civil Affairs; by their Abſurd and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152814:3"/>diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> (of which laſt they have alwaies made themſelves ſole Judges) they mangle the Kings Authority, and as to <hi>Church-matters</hi> (which may be extended as far as they pleaſe) they leave the King nothing of <hi>Supremacy</hi> but the Name. The <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> therefore (who is the great Father of all ſuch Biſhops) hath improved this Notion and Diſtinction ſo farre that <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> he hath laboured to ſubject all Civil Empires unto his ſole Juriſdiction. So that if the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Rule hold good, of <hi>Crimine ab uno</hi> —<hi>Diſce omnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 21.</note> i.e. <hi>That all men who are of a Party may be judged of by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of one,</hi> then I muſt leave it to You to judge, what all thoſe Biſhops, that are of the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, really drive at, by the fatal example of that one Biſhops Uſurpation: For</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Aſſertion, <hi>that the Biſhop of Worceſter</hi> (and conſequently every other Biſhop) <hi>is the ſole Paſtor of all the Congregations in his Dioceſs,</hi> if it be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all defenſible,<note place="margin">Pag. 2, &amp; 3.</note> I am ſure can be defended only by thoſe Arguments; which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly alleadged to maintain the <hi>Popes Supremacy</hi> over all Churches whatever. For ſince a Biſhop can no otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his duty herein, then by providing <hi>Subſtitutes,</hi> what hinders but the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> may as well overſee a million of Churches, as the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> five hundred? Since if Deputation be lawfull, more or leſſe compaſſe and circuit of ground doth not at all alter the caſe. I forbear to urge how contrary this Practiſe is to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, both <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> (I hope the Biſhop will not take it ill that I do not call them <hi>Saints,</hi> for theſe <hi>Holy men</hi> do not need any ſtile of Honour out of the <hi>Popes Kalender.</hi>) When <hi>Paul</hi> had ſent for the <hi>Elders of the Church at Epheſus,</hi> he bids them <hi>to feed the Church of God, over which</hi> (not he himſelf,<note place="margin">Act. 20 28.</note> by his ſole Authority, as Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, but) <hi>the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152814:4"/>Spirit of God had made them</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> i. e. <hi>Overſeers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2.</note> or to uſe the proper ſtile, <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> commands his <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Elders,</hi> (for ſo doth that Apoſtle condeſcend to call himſelf) <hi>to feed the Flock which was among them,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Overſeeing,</hi> or <hi>Acting the Biſhops, not</hi> (like the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>) <hi>as Lording it over Gods Heritage, but as Patterns of the Flock.</hi> From which places we learn, not only that thoſe two ſo much controverted Names of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> are without diſtinction aſcribed to the ſame Perſons, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that whoever <hi>feed the Flock,</hi> are, <hi>under Christ</hi> (whom the Apoſtle there ſtiles the <hi>Chief-Shepherd</hi>) the next and immediate <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the <hi>Flock;</hi> and to extend the <hi>Paſtoral Power</hi> beyond the actual care of <hi>Feeding,</hi> is a Notion altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unſcriptural, and likewiſe leaves us no bounds where to fix, till we come to center upon ſome one <hi>Univerſal Paſtor,</hi> who may claim this Power over the whole world, by the ſame parity of reaſon, that a Biſhop doth over one <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It ſeems to be a Light, and (to ſay no more) unſeemly trifling with ſacred Scripture, to affirm that thoſe words of our Saviour concerning ſuch as <hi>come not in by the door,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> and therefore <hi>are Theeves and Robbers,</hi> ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ſuch <hi>Ministers, as preach to Congregations without the Biſhops Licenſe.</hi> Which thing, the Biſhop (in great Heat and Earneſtneſſe, as if he had done very well in it) tels us more then once,<note place="margin">P. 3, 6, 8, &amp; 9.</note> that it was <hi>the Principal reaſon why he ſilenced</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> Truly if this practiſe be juſtifiable, and thoſe who deſign themſelves <hi>to preach the Goſpel,</hi> muſt, beſides their <hi>Ordination,</hi> procure <hi>a Licenſe from a Biſhop,</hi> to do that, which a <hi>Woe</hi> is denounced againſt, if they offer to omit, then 1. I ſee not what <hi>Ordination</hi> ſignifies, ſince the Power that then is given, no Authority from Man can take away, any more then diſſolve the Contract of a Marriage, much leſſe empeach
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152814:4"/>and hinder the free uſe of it, except for Moral and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vicious Miſdemeanours. 2. For one <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel</hi> (for certainly a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is no more) to Silence another, and that for no better Reaſon, then becauſe his Fellow-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is deſirous to preach the Goſpel without a <hi>new Licenſe,</hi> this is an abuſe of Dominion, which as our Saviour doth no where countenance, ſo the firſt Ages of the Church were altogether unacquainted with. For the <hi>Biſhops</hi> inſtance of our Saviours <hi>putting to ſilence the Scribes and Phariſees</hi> is both Impertinent and Falſe, becauſe our Saviour did only <hi>ſilence them by Argument,</hi> which the Biſhop may do whenever he is able; but what is that to an Authoritative and Imperious commanding men to be Silent. Beſides, even then when our Saviour was moſt ſtrict in pronouncing <hi>Woes</hi> againſt the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> in that very Chapter, he is ſo far from forbidding the <hi>Phariſees</hi> to preach, that he commands his Diſciples both to Hear and to Obey their Doctrine. So that ſince the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop will needs have the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to be <hi>Phariſees,</hi> let him but allow them the ſame Liberty of Teaching the People, as our Saviour did the other, and I believe they will not (at leaſt were I a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> I ſhould not) envy his Lordſhip, either his Tide or Maintenance, how undue and unmerited ſoever they both be. And though the Biſhop is pleaſed to ſay that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> preach nothing but <hi>Sedition and Treaſon</hi> (which is moſt falſe, as being directly contrary to their declared Principles) yet the <hi>Phariſees</hi> taught ſomething worſe, and that was <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> Yet our Saviour (who ſure had more power, and withall, more care of his Church then the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>) did not go about by Force to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit them. I wiſh therefore, that this Biſhop and the reſt of his Brethren (if any are Cholerick and Teſty enough to be of his mind) would conſider, that as by ſilencing their <hi>Fellow-Miniſters,</hi> for ſuch frivolous and ſlight pretences, they uſurp
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152814:5"/>a Power, which Chriſt never gave, ſo at the laſt day he will not thank them for the Exerciſe of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, How conſiſtent with the <hi>Civil Peace</hi> (for as to <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 8.</note> the whole thing is but a <hi>Letter of defiance</hi> againſt it) the <hi>Biſhops Diſtinction</hi> is about the <hi>Act of Indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and (the ſo much forgotten) <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> I hope his Majeſty and the Parliament will in due time conſider. For he is ſo hardy as to tell us, <hi>That the King by it, only pardoned the corporal Puniſhment; but the Church had not, nor ought not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the Scandal, till honourable amends were made her by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion and Recantation.</hi> Where by ſpeaking of the <hi>Church,</hi> as diſtinct from the <hi>State</hi> (I mean in point of <hi>Coercive Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi>) the Biſhop would make us believe, that after his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the Parliament have forgiven men their Civil Crimes, there is ſtill another Power, which he calls <hi>the Church,</hi> unto which they are ſtill accountable, even ſo far as to make a <hi>Publick Recantation.</hi> Here I wiſh the Biſhop would have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Clouds, and plainly told us, what he meant by <hi>the Church:</hi> For if it be <hi>a Congregation of the Faithful met together for the Worſhip of God,</hi> as the Definition of Scripture, and of the <hi>Church of England</hi> is in the 39 Articles; this will not at all advantage him, ſince ſuch a Church hath no Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive or Impoſing Power: But if he means the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical State,</hi> by <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. there can be nothing more Falſe, or more diſhonourable unto our Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, than to affirm that it lies in their power, not only to Puniſh, but likewiſe to exact a <hi>Recantation,</hi> for thoſe Faults which the <hi>King and Parliament</hi> have not only pardoned, but under ſevere Penalties commanded ſhould never more be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: And therefore I doubt not, but they will reſent this Malicious and Ill-grounded Fancy. And ſince the Biſhop is ſo over-zealous for the very Letter of the Law, when it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> give me leave a little to wonder, that one of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152814:5"/>his Profeſſion and Place in the Church ſhould ſo unchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go againſt it, when it enjoyns Moderation and Forgiveneſs as to Civil Injuries. Such as he, who make the Law, inſtead of being a <hi>Buckler</hi> to protect <hi>Converts,</hi> a <hi>Sword</hi> only to cut off all ſuch as were once Offenders, labour what they can to make men Deſperate, and thereby render the Peace of the Nation, and, in that, the Proſperity and Welfare of his Majeſty very Inſecure and Hazardous. For what can more enrage Men to take Wild and Forbidden courſes, then to ſee even Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Goſpel ſtrive to widen their Wounds, and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own former Profeſſions, to pull off that Plaiſter, which the Wiſdom of our State Phyſicians had provided to heal our Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is Bold and Impious (I know not how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it more mildly) what he affirms,<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> that <hi>If to command an Act, which by accident may prove an occaſion of ſin, be ſinful, then God himſelf cannot command any thing.</hi> For, though as I ſaid before, I will by no means own that Aſſertion, yet, a thing, which by accident may become ſinful, may be Unlawful, in another to command, for want of ſufficient Authority. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Gods Sovereign power doth without diſpute or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie make all his Commands to be Juſt; and therefore his Name ought not to be mentioned in our trivial diſputes, becauſe every ſuch vain Uſe of it, is nothing but a diminution and leſſening of his Greatneſs.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>That an Offence, to which a diſproportionable Penalty is annexed, is not to be meaſured by the Quality of the Act conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in it ſelf, but by the miſchievous conſequences it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce;</hi> whether this ought to hold good in <hi>Civil Laws,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes neither the Biſhop nor me to diſpute: but in <hi>Divinity</hi> nothing can be more Falſe and Dangerous. For to impoſe, in the Worſhip of God as neceſſary circumſtances of it, things confeſſedly trivial and needleſs; and, upon the forbearance of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152814:6"/>them, to debar any from the benefits firſt of Chriſtian; and then of Civil Communion; is a thing which hath not the leaſt pretence of Scripture or Primitive practice to juſtifie it. For our Saviour tells us, That <hi>whoever were not against him, were for him;</hi> and the Apoſtle bids us <hi>to receive our weak Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not to judge,</hi> much leſs to <hi>burden his Conſcience.</hi> Unto which <hi>Sacred Canon,</hi> nothing can be more directly contrary, then what the Biſhop moſt Incompaſſionately tells us, <hi>That the Laws do well to puniſh, even with non-admiſsion to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſuch as will not, or perhaps dare not, kneel.</hi> And the Reaſon he gives<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is equally <hi>Apocrypha, Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not the Law-givers to endanger the Churches peace for their ſake:</hi> As if firſt, It did not much more become all Law-givers, in the things of God, to obſerve the Law of Chriſt, which is a Law of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Liberty.</hi> Secondly, As if the Churches peace would not be much more endangered, by the Preſſing of things doubtful, than by the forbearance of them. For ſince by the enforcing of ſuch things, as God hath no where commanded, our Chriſtian liberty is enfringed; from hence it follows, that, if we ought not, yet we lawfully may refuſe, to ſubmit unto ſuch Impoſitions; as our Saviour did, <hi>in not waſhing his hands before Meat;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Circumciſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, As for the chaine of Conſequences, which the Biſhop links and ties together.<note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> As that <hi>from Diverſity in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rites, ariſeth Diſlike; from Diſlike, Enmity; from Enmity, Oppoſition; thence, Schiſm in the Church, and Sedition in the State:</hi> For proof of which he doth very virulently inſtance in our Unhappy times. To prevent which, he tells us, That <hi>the State cannot be ſafe without the Church, nor the Church without Unity, nor Unity without Uniformity, nor Uniformity without a ſtrict and rigorous Impoſition.</hi> To all this I anſwer, that it is a meer Rope of Sand, and the Parts of his Chain do as little
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152814:6"/>hang together, as <hi>Sampſons Foxes</hi> did before they were tied by the Tailes, which courſe the Biſhop hath imitated, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting to put in even the <hi>Firebrand</hi> it ſelf to make up the compariſon. For 1. Nothing is more clear than that there hath been, nay ought to be, <hi>Diverſity in external Forms,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Diſlike</hi> at all as to the Perſon of another: For the <hi>Apoſtles that preached to the Circumciſion</hi> gave the right of Fellowſhip unto the <hi>Apoſtles of the Gentiles;</hi> although their <hi>Outward Rites</hi> in publick Worſhip, were far more different, than thoſe, which, by any of the moſt diſtant perſwaſions, are now practiſed in <hi>England.</hi> 2. The <hi>State</hi> may be preſerved, without the leaſt reference to the <hi>Church,</hi> unleſs it turns Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter of it; as is evident in thoſe 300 years before <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> time, in which there was no Church at all legally coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced; and for ſome ſcores of years after, both the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> were equally advanced and favoured. 3. <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> I mean ſuch as Chriſt came to eſtabliſh (which is an <hi>Unity</hi> in heart and ſpirit) doth not in the leaſt depend upon <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> but upon <hi>Charity, i.e,</hi> a Chriſtian and a Candid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of one another in things <hi>Circumſtantial,</hi> when we agree in the <hi>Eſſentials of Worſhip;</hi> which is a thing, that meer Civility would teach, though Religion were ſilent in it. And whereas the Biſhop thinks he hath got ſome advantage, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving the memory of our late <hi>Civil Wars</hi> which, were he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian or Man enough, he would wiſh, were eternally buried in ſilence) I muſt (to uſe his own Phraſe) <hi>tell him in his ear,</hi> that our Wars did not ariſe from the ſeparation of Conſcientious Diſſentors, but from the violence and Fury of Unconſcionable Impoſers: Who would not allow their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (who deſired nothing more than to live peaceably by them) that ſober Liberty, which the <hi>Law of God</hi> commanded, and no Law of Man could juſtly deprive them of. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the publick maintaining of the very ſame Poſitions and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152814:7"/>Practiſes, may not in time beget the ſame Feuds and Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, although, this Biſhop cares not, yet I doubt not, but his Majeſty, as he now doth, ſo will alwaies graciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Whether, as to the matter of Fact, the <hi>French Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> do enjoyn <hi>ſtanding</hi> at the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> &amp; the <hi>Dutch, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> I will labour to enform my ſelf of ſome more Unbyaſſed witneſs than this Biſhop; for in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws</hi> of thoſe <hi>Churches,</hi> which I have carefully peruſed, I can find no ſuch matter. But if they did ſo, this would not at all juſtifie the Impoſition of <hi>Kneeling;</hi> becauſe 1. The Queſtion is <hi>de Jure,</hi> whether it be lawful to preſcribe any one ſuch certain Poſture, without ſubmitting to which, it ſhall not be lawful to admit any to the Sacrament, and till the Affirmative of this be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Scriptures, Examples, and Inſtances from the Practice of men, will not ſatisfie a doubting conſcience. 2, Neither of thoſe fore mentioned Poſtures are ſo much to exception as <hi>Kneeling;</hi> becauſe this laſt is manifeſtly more ſuperſtitious, for 1. It varies moſt of any from the <hi>Firſt Pattern.</hi> 2. It hath been monſtrouſly abuſed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to <hi>Idolatry;</hi> which alone renders it moſt Unſafe to be practiſed, and moſt Unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable to be impoſed: Eſpecially, till it be again explained, as in the very firſt <hi>Liturgy</hi> of all it was; which I particularly mention, to ſhew how little our <hi>Reformation</hi> ſince <hi>Edw.</hi> 6th. time, hath been improved.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As it was needleſly, ſo was it likewiſe Uncharitably done, to revile the whole body of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> for the Faults of Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> upon ſuppoſition that either he is a <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> or ſo culpable as the Biſhop would make him. For ſince every man is <hi>to bear his own Burden,</hi> what Bible did the Biſhop find it in, that he might, without ſcruple, aſperſe a whole or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Men, for the pretended miſcarriage of one; who, by the Biſhop's own Confeſſion, was not of ſo Amicable and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152814:7"/>compliant a Temper as the reſt: And therefore certainly they ought not to be brought in as Parties in that crime of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaceableneſs, from which the Biſhop juſt before had abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them: but choler ſpoyls the Memory; and, ſure his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Biſhops would not take it well of a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> ſhould he cry out <hi>Crimine ab uno, diſce omnes—See what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spirit theſe Biſhops are of, and judge them all by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Worceſters example.</hi> Truly, Sir. I am a little angry, when I conſider how much this one mans Indiſcretion hath expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all of the ſame Order to Cenſure; For were they all like him (which I do not, nor dare not think) I ſhould not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray heartily, what the <hi>Biſhop</hi> doth in ſcorn concerning the Preachers — <hi>Lord deliver us from ſuch Biſhops.</hi> And let all the People ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, you ſee how willing I am to ſerve you in propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my Exceptions, the fuller proſecution of which I muſt leave to ſome other Pen, more able both in <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Policy;</hi> who may convince, both the Biſhop and the World, that it is not yet time to ſow ſuch <hi>Tares;</hi> This Age is a little too know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be gulled, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or to take every thing for Oracle which a Biſhops Paſſion dictates. But before I eaſe you of your Trouble in reading this, I will crave leave to give you a Taſte of the <hi>Reverend Father's</hi> deep wiſdom in two or three particulars —</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that he declaimes, ſo fiercely, as if he would crack his Girdle, againſt all thoſe <hi>who force all Communicants to come unto them and be particularly examined before they admit them to the Sacrament.</hi> Indeed, Sir, this was an Impoſition, as no way Juſtifiable, ſo, for ought I can hear, no where practiſed. The Cuſtome being that men were only once for all examined, at their firſt coming to the Sacrament; which the Biſhop him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf allows under other Names of being Catechiſed and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. It was therefore wiſely done or the Biſhop, this cold
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152814:8"/>weather, to ſet up a <hi>Man of ſtraw,</hi> and then get himſelf heat by threſhing it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is me-thinks very Politickly done to Exclaime againſt the poor <hi>Covenant;</hi> and, in great zeal, to wiſh all the <hi>Books, which defend it, were burnt by the Authors, to ſave the Hangman a labour.</hi> For here let his Adverſary do what he can, the Biſhop will be too hard for him: For if he takes no notice of the Covenant, the Biſhop clearly gains the Cauſe, if he ventures to aſſert it, he ſhall preſently be confuted with a Confiſcation. So that under the ſhelter of this Unanſwerable <hi>Dilemma</hi> I leave him, leſt I ſhould be gored with the Horns of it. And this I ſpeak, Sir, as one that, though I never took, but alwaies oppoſed the <hi>Covenant;</hi> yet I have a very good opinion of many that did, and withal a great Tenderneſs for the lawful Part of an Oath, after it is once ſolemnly taken. I will only adde this, That ſince that Oath hath been ſo generally taken, even by thoſe that were moſt Active in his late Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and ſeveral times ventured their Lives, to ſignalize their Loyalty; I think the Aſhes of it (ſince it was burnt by Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority) had much better have been ſuffered to reſt quietly, than thus to be blown up and ſcattered abroad by the Biſhop's furious Breath, when no occaſion was given him ſo much as to mention it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I can never enough commend the Biſhops wiſdom, in reſolving ſo angrily never to write again; for he is Old, and hath Travelled far, and knows that it is much eaſier to ſpeak raſh and unjuſtifiable things than to defend them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deals with thoſe, that he hath provoked, as witty School-boyes do wiſh their Companions, firſt he hits them a box on the Ear, and then very diſcreetly retreats, and fairly runs away But if <hi>Goliah,</hi> who took upon him to defie the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhould, as ſoon as ever he had done, have ſneaked out of the Field, and thought he had done manfully enough
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152814:8"/>in making a Bold Challenge, and in ſhewing his Teeth at them; I believe the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> would hardly have thanked him for that Empty ſhew of Valour, whereby he could not Conquer, but only enrage the Enemy. And whether the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops will not have the ſame opinion of this over-forward and unwary Champion of theirs, I hope, Sir, you will neither en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire your ſelf, nor deſire that I ſhould: For I have already done enough to ſhew how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 21.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SIR, Your moſt humble Servant D. E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
